Guide to the Department of Psychology and Neuroscience Records, 1930-1996 UA.25.34.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Department of Psychology and Neuroscience records
1930-1996
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Department of Psychology and Neuroscience
UA.25.34.0001
8.5 Linear Feet
The Department of Psychology and Neuroscience at Duke features scholarship and teaching in several subdisciplines of psychology and is the primary home for the study of the neuroscience of behavior in the College of Arts & Sciences. This collection contains minutes from various subgroups within the Psychology Department, staff meetings, clinical psychology staff meetings, senior staff committee meetings, and graduate staff meetings, as well as, departmental correspondence, applications for research grants, class census records, reports to the administration and the Board of Trustees, videotapes, 16mm film, and publications of the Psychology Department faculty.
7000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Provenance
The Department of Psychology and Neuroscience Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer starting in 1974.
Historical Note
The mission of the undergraduate program in psychology at Duke University is to provide students with a dynamic and interactive learning experience that confers a strong background in psychology as a science. Graduate training in Psychology and Neuroscience at Duke provides students with exceptional opportunities to examine mind, brain, and behavior at different levels of analysis (e.g., neural, molecular, individual, and social) using a variety of techniques (e.g., brain imaging, animal models, computational models, experimental research with humans, surveys, and field studies). The Duke Psychology Department was created in 1927 with William McDougall serving as its first chair.
Collection Overview
This collection contains minutes from various subgroups within the Psychology Department, staff meetings, clinical psychology staff meetings, senior staff committee meetings, and graduate staff meetings, as well as, departmental correspondence, applications for research grants, class census records, reports to the administration and the Board of Trustees, videotapes, 16mm film, and publications of the Psychology Department faculty. Materials span date from 1930-1996 with the bulk dates of 1949-1980. Video and film materials are undated.
Related Material
Parapsychology Labratory Records
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Parapsychology Laboratory; Duke University. Psychology Department; Duke University. Department of Psychology and Neuroscience; Duke University. Psychology Department -- Faculty
- Department of Psychology and Neuroscience, Administrative files, 1930-1996, 8.5 Linear Feet; 12 boxes
  - Parapsychology, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1981, 1988, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Handbook for Graduate Students of Color, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Memos, Majors Info, Departmental Advisors Information,1958-1968 (Box 1)
  - Memoranda, Flyers, Etc.,1960-1994 (Box 1)
  - Undergraduate Guide,1985-1991 (Box 1)
  - Course Papers, Psych 271A (Neuropsychology),1972 (Box 1)
  - Clinical Psychology Staff Meeting Minutes,1957-1965 (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - Senior Staff Committee Meetings,1958-1960 (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Graduate Staff Meeting, General Staff Meetings,1962-1966 (Box 2)
  - Staff Meetings,1949-1962 (13 folders) (Box 3)
  - Department Staff Meetings,1964-1967 (Box 3)
  - Curriculum Revision, Clinical Training in Mental Assessment,1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Clinical Psychology Staff Meetings,1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - Faculty Publications, Reprints, etc.
    - Adams, Donald (Box 4)
    - Borstelman, Lloyd (Box 4)
    - Cohen, Louis D. (Box 4)
    - Costanzo, Philip R. (Box 4)
    - Crovitz, Elaine (Box 4)
    - Daston, Paul (Box 4)
    - Guttman, Norman (Box 4)
    - Kalat, James W. (Box 4)
    - Kuder, G. Frederic (Box 4)
    - Lodge, Ann (Box 4)
    - Lundholm, Helge (Box 4)
    - Pratt, J.G. (Box 4)
    - Reichenberg-Hacket, Wally (Box 4)
    - Parapsychology Lab - Reprints,1930-1955 (Box 4)
    - Spielberger, Charles D. (Box 4)
    - Staddon, John E.R. (Box 4)
    - Wallach, Michael A. (Box 4)
    - Widgery, Alban G. (Box 4)
  - Parapsychology Laboratory
    Scope and Contents note
    The Duke Parapsychology lab opened in 1935 and in 1965 it closed at Duke and moved to the the foundation for research on the Nature of Man as the Institute for Parapsychology. Please see the Parasychology Labratory Records for more information: url="http://library.duke.edu/rubenstein/findingaids/paralab/
    - Rhine, J.B., Parapsychology: From Duke to FRNM., (book), 1965 (Box 5)
    - Rhine, J.B., Extra-Sensory Perception After Sixty Years, (book), 1940 (Box 5)
    - Rhine, J.B., The Reach of the Mind, (book), 1947 (Box 5)
    - Rhine, Louisa E., ESP in Life and Lab: Tracing Hidden Channels,(book), 1967 (Box 5)
    - Pratt, J. Gaither., Parapsychology: An Insider's View of ESP, (book), 1964 (Box 5)
    - Alexander, Irving - Personal Correspondence (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - American Association of State Psychology Boards, 1968 (Box 6)
    - American Association of University Professors, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
    - American Psychological Association, correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 6)
    - Bivins Building Floor Plan (5 oversize blueprints) (Box 6)
    - Council of Chairmen of Graduate Departments of Psychology (A.P.A.), 1965-1967 (Box 6)
    - Building and Space, correspondence with NIMH about Facilities Grants 1961-1962 (Box 6)
    - Building and Space, memorandum to Library Council re: Reference room in Biology, 1962 (Box 6)
    - Building and Space, memoranda re: Relocation of Department, 1961 (Box 6)
    - Child Guidance Clinic, 1949-1957 (Box 6)
    - NSF - Final Report - 1964 (Box 6)
    - Class Census Reports, 1951-1961 (11 folders) (Box 7)
    - Colloquium Notices,Prior to 1951 (Box 7)
    - Colloquium Notices,1965-1969 (4 folders) (Box 7)
    - Correspondence with Dean Anlyan1964-1965 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence with Provost Taylor Cole1964-1965 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence with Senator Erwin1964-1968 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence with President Douglas Knight1965 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence with Dean Lewis1968 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence with Dean Predmore Re: Graduate School1964-1965 (Box 7)
    - Council Gerontology1964-1965 (Box 7)
    - Educational Improvement Project (Box 7)
    - Graduate Council, 1949-1969 (Box 8)
    - North Carolina Academy of Science, 1950-1952 (Box 8)
    - Parapsychology Lab Clippings & Correspondence, 1934-1964 (Box 8)
    - The Participant Observer - Newsletter of the Graduate Student Club, 1964-1965 (Box 8)
    - Personal - NSF Grant Application (Box 8)
    - Personal - Grant Correspondence, 1962, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Planning - Clinical Counseling, 1960 (Box 8)
    - Political Science, 1967 (Box 8)
    - Hopkins Folly, Regional Educational Laboratory, 1965-1968 (Box 8)
    - Report to Board of Trustees, March 5, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Zener - papers, research proposals, n.d., 1947-1964 (Box 8)
    - Zener, K.E., papers submitted to Research Council, n.d. (Box 8)
    - Zener, K.E. - Papers, 1930-1950 (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Dept. memos, flyers, clippings, 1958-1979 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Files
    Faculty files include correspondence, publications, hirings, and terminations. Administrative records are restricted for 25 years from their date of origin. Please contact research services for more information.
    - Adams, Donald K. (Box 9)
    - Altrocchi, John C. (Associate Professor)(3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Axelrod, Seymour (Box 9)
    - Bobbitt, Joseph M. (Box 9)
    - Boneau, C. Alan (Associate Professor) (Box 9)
    - Botwinick, Jack (Lecturer in Psychology) (Box 9)
    - Burkheimer, Graham J., Jr. (Lecturer)1972 (Box 9)
    - Cochrane, Carl M. (Box 9)
    - Cohen, Louis D. (Box 9)
    - Cohen, Sanford(2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Collier, George (Box 9)
    - Conger, Anthony (Visiting Associate Professor), 1973-1974 (Box 9)
    - Conger, Judith C. (Visiting Assistant Professor), 1971-1972 (Box 9)
    - Dai, Bingham (Professor)(2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Daniel, Mariel (Box 9)
    - Dashiell, John F. (Box 9)
    - Daston, Paul (Box 9)
    - DeVoge, Justin Thomas,1971 (Box 9)
    - Diamond, I.T. (Box 9)
    - Edwards, Curtis Drew (Lecturer), 1975 (Box 9)
    - Eisdorfer, Carl (Lecturer), 1958 (Box 9)
    - Eisdorfer, Carl (Lecturer) - scholarly papers (Box 9)
    - Farina, Amerigo (Box 10)
    - Feather, Ben W. (Lecturer), 1966 (Box 10)
    - Ferguson, Lucy (Visiting Professor), 1974-1975 (Box 10)
    - Filer, Robert J. (Box 10)
    - Gallagher, James, 1966-1967 (Box 10)
    - Garmezy, Norman (Box 10)
    - Giora, Zvi (Visiting Scholar), 1975-1976 (Box 10)
    - Glendenning, Robert L. (Research Associate, Lecturer), 1973-1974 (Box 10)
    - Goffard, S. James (Box 10)
    - Greenwood, Donald (Assistant Professor), 1964 (Box 10)
    - Harting, John K. (Research Associate), 1971 (Box 10)
    - Heider, Fritz (Box 10)
    - Hemmes, Richard, 1972 (Box 10)
    - Hester, William (Box 10)
    - Hetherington, Duncan (Box 10)
    - Howes, Davis H. (Visiting Professor), 1974 (Box 10)
    - Huse, Mary (Lecturer),1959 (Box 10)
    - Jones, Lyle V. (Box 10)
    - Kalish, Harry I. (Box 10)
    - Kinsbourne, Marcel (Lecturer), 1966 (Box 10)
    - Kinsbourne, D.M. - Publications and Reprints (Box 10)
    - Kimmel, Herbert D. (Box 10)
    - Klopfer, Walter (Box 10)
    - Koch, Sigmund (Professor) (Box 10)
    - Kohler, Ivo (Box 10)
    - Kolesnik, Bohdan P. (Box 10)
    - Kramer, Richard B. (Asst. Professor), 1968- (Box 10)
    - Kramer, R.B. - "Faces" Grant, 1970 (Box 10)
    - Kruglanski, Arie - Summer Term I (Box 10)
    - Krugman, Arnold D. (Lecturer), 1964 (Box 10)
    - Kuder, G. Frederic (Box 10)
    - Linder, Darwin (Associate),1965 (Box 10)
    - Lodge, George T. (Box 10)
    - Lundholm, Helge (Box 10)
    - McCurdy, Harold (Box 10)
    - McHugh, Gelolo (Associate Professor), 1946- (Box 10)
    - Mehryar, Amir H. (Visiting), 1977-1978 (Box 10)
    - Meltzer, Macolm L., 1963 (Box 10)
    - Murphy, Daniel (Box 10)
    - Obrist, Walter (Lecturer), 1960 (Box 10)
    - Obrist, Walter (Lecturer) - Publications & Reprints (Box 10)
    - Parsons, Oscar A. (Box 10)
    - Perry, Martha (Lecturer), 1972 (Box 10)
    - Randall, Walter (Box 10)
    - Randall, Walter (Box 11)
    - Rhine, J.B. (Box 11)
    - Reichenberg, Wally (Box 11)
    - Robinson, Nancy Mayer (Box 11)
    - Rodnick, Eliot H. (Box 11)
    - Schonbach, Peter Michael (Box 11)
    - Shmavonian, Barry (Lecturer),1958- (Box 11)
    - Shmavonian, Barry (Lecturer) - Publications & Reprints (Box 11)
    - Simmell, Marianne (Box 11)
    - Singer, David L. (Box 11)
    - Singer, David L. - Publications & Reprints (Box 11)
    - Sperling, George (Box 11)
    - Spielberger, Charles (Box 11)
    - Spielberger & Weitz - Mental Health Project Grant Progress Report,1972 (Box 11)
    - Stedman, Donald (Lecturer) (Box 11)
    - Stedman, Donald (Lecturer) - Publications & Reprints (Box 11)
    - Stern, William - Bibliography, booklet, 1936-1938 (Box 11)
    - Stotsky, Bernard (Box 11)
    - Strong, Paschal (Box 11)
    - Strupp, Hans (Box 11)
    - Thompson, Larry (Lecturer) (Box 11)
    - Vogel, John L. (Box 11)
    - Weisskopf-Joelson (Visiting Professor) (Box 11)
    - Weitz, Henry (Bureau of Testing and Guidance) (Box 11)
    - Wheeler, Ladd (Box 11)
    - Wilson, Kellogg (Box 11)
    - Wortman, Paul M. (Assistant Professor), 1967- (Box 11)
  - Graduate Students Club, 1964-1966 (Box 11)
  - Department Brochures, Clippings, Directories, Faculty Correspondence,1953-1977 (Box 11)
  - Video Materials
    An access copy will be necessary to review these materials, please contact Research Services before you visit the reading room.
    - Raccoons (TRT: 64:00) (Box 12)
    - Erisman and Kohler, Inverting Prisms (Box 12)
    - Three Approaches to Psychotherapy, Part 1 Carl Rogers (RT: 47:52), Part 2 Frederick Perls (RT: 31:58), Part 3 Albert Ellis (RT: 36:08) (Box 12)
    - McDougall, Raccoons (16mm Film) (Box 12)
    - Experimental Psychology of Vision (Box 12)
    - Depth Factors (Shadows, Iinterposition, Convergence, Accomodation) (Box 12)
    - Erisman and Kohler, Inverting Prisms (Box 12)
    - Erisman and Kohler, Upright Vision Through Inverting Spectacles: Silent (TRT: 160:00) (Box 12)